# 大家好 今天攝影小哥家的房子哦 做子個樓頂啊
Hi everyone! Today, Mr. Cameraman’s house, they’re making the, the rooftop,
# 不是樓頂 這是第一屋的頂
no, not the rooftop, but the roof of the first floor.
# 我們過來幫一下忙
We’re coming to give a hand.
# 好多人都上去啦
Many people are already up there.
# 我也過來幫一下忙
And I’m going as well.
# 這個是主樑哦 要把這個
This is the main pillar. It needs to be,
# 這個 水泥要把它灌進去
the, the cement needs to be poured inside.
# 不灌進去
Otherwise,
# 不灌進去沒用的
it's useless otherwise.
# 現在快搞完啦 還有一個小時左右就可以搞得完啦
It’s almost finished now. It will be finished in about an hour.
# 我去搞點Wo笋來煮飯 (註︰這應該是茭白，萵笋應該是方言叫法，為免混亂，以茭白翻譯，下面有一堆用顯微鏡才看到的附註，不譯了)
Let me get some wild rice for our meal,
(Wild rice: Zizania latifolia, also know as Manchurian wild rice)
# 煮晚飯
for our dinner.
# 在前面那一點
It’s over there a bit in the front.
# 馬上就天黑啦 你看
It’s getting dark now. Look!
# 我去搞點那個WO笋 就在那邊
Let me get some wild rice. It’s right over there.
# 你看 這個就是WO笋哦
Look! This is wild rice.
# 誒 被兄弟拔啦
Eh? It was picked by my buddy.
# 有肉的 這個
It is edible, this one.
# 你看 這個是有肉的看見沒有 好嫩的哦 這個
Look! It has an edible part. See? This one is really young and tender, you know.
# 直接就可以吃啊 可以當水果吃
It can be eaten right away, as fruits.
# 有點甘甜甘甜的味道
It tastes a bit savoury and sweet.
# 你看 剛長出來很嫩的
Look! It has just grown out from the soil. It’s still very young.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以
Not bad!
# 你看 就這一點點
Look! It’s just a tiny little bit here.
# 夠嫩吧 這樣才好吃
It’s young, isn’t it? That’s why it is tasty.
# 就那一點點夠啦
Just a tiny little bit here is enough.
# 就這一點點 肚子大的 這個
Just a tiny little bit here, with a big belly, this one.
# 嗯 我們就要這一點點
Um! We only take this tiny little bit here.
# 看起來不要看它的肚子稍微小一點
Although its belly looks a little bit small,
# 這個全是肉哇 看到沒有
everything here can be eaten, see?
# 這就是肉 看到沒有
This part can be eaten, see?
# 啊 這個肉
Ah! It’s really nice.
# 金[SIC]瑩剔透的肉
Crystal clear
# 乳白色的肉
And milky white
# 很嫩的
It’s really young and tender.
# 啊 這個就是標準身材 剛剛好
Oh! This is the standard build. Everything is perfect.
# 你看 可以吧 (註︰我聽到他說︰「可以了」
Look! It’s alright now.
# 嗯 可以
Um! It’s not bad.
# 這裡比較多
There are quite a lot here.
# 沒多少 就那麼一丟丟
Not too much. Just a tiny little bit here.
# 這個都不是很大 可能 不是很熟
And they’re not really that big. Perhaps, they’re not completely ripe.
# 但是太熟了又會老掉
But they would be too old if they’re completely ripe.
# 所以我也很糾結
So I’m always struggling.
# 你看 就搞了那麼一點點
Look! So we’ve taken just a tiny little bit here.
# 它現在不是很 很老哦
Now they’re not really, really old.
# 下次來
Next time.
# 讓它們也長肥一點 我再來
I’ll come again, after they have grown fatter.
# 現在不是很胖
They’re not really that fat now.